Guide to the University of Chicago Department of Botany Records 1882-1972
University of Chicago Library
University of Chicago. Department of Botany. Records
1882-1972
62.5 linear feet (67 boxes, 1 slide cabinet)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Founded in 1894 under the leadership of John M. Coulter, The University of Chicago Department of Botany quickly grew to become one of modern botany's most influential centers of research and teaching. The work of Henry C. Cowles and others associated with the Chicago school of ecology is generally regarded as one of the most influential forces in the development of ecological studies. This collection includes administrative files, publications, memorabilia and artifacts, and a large collection of photographs documenting plant life, environmental phenomena, and departmental activities.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Historical Note
In 1894, University of Chicago President William Rainey Harper appointed John Merle Coulter (1851-1928) to lead the newly established Department of Botany. Coulter was a leading American botanist and a friend of Asa Gray (1810-1888), the famed Harvard botanist whose Manual of Botany and other texts dominated plant science in the United States. Coulter had founded the Botanical Gazette nearly twenty years earlier, and he brought the editorship of the professional journal with him to his new position. In 1896, botanical research at the University of Chicago was further enhanced with the erection of the Hull Biological Laboratories. This complex of four buildings included the Botany Building, which housed classrooms, labs, and a rooftop greenhouse, and Botany Pond, an adjacent outdoor plant study facility.
The University of Chicago's Department of Botany quickly grew to become one of modern botany's most influential centers of research and teaching. By the 1930s, the roster of notable researchers serving on the Botany faculty included Henry C. Cowles and George D. Fuller in ecology, Charles J. Chamberlain in plant morphology, Merle C. Coulter in plant genetics, Adolf C. Noe in paleobotany, and Charles Barnes, William Crocker, and Charles A. Shull in plant physiology. The Botanical Gazette, published under the direction of an editorial board drawn from the department's faculty, was American botany's leading journal, and national university evaluations such as the Hughes Report of 1925 ranked the Department of Botany first among its academic peers.
None of the Department of Botany's achievements loomed larger than the new field of plant ecology developed by Henry Chandler Cowles (1869-1939). Cowles was a graduate student of John M. Coulter, a member of the Botany faculty from 1897 onward, and chairman of the department from 1925 until his retirement in 1934.
Cowles's formulation of ecology was first expressed in his Ph.D. thesis, "The Ecological Relations of the Vegetation on the Sand Dunes of Lake Michigan" (1898). Cowles based his thesis on detailed field work he had undertaken in the Indiana Dunes, a wild, unsettled region of beaches, sand dunes, bogs, and woods along the southern shore of Lake Michigan about twenty-five miles from the University of Chicago. Cowles argued that the natural succession of plant forms in time could be traced in physical space as one moved inland from the open lake beach across ancient shorelines through the shifting dunes to the interior forest.
Henry C. Cowles and his theories and methods attracted many students to the Department of Botany, and these students in turn secured positions at other
universities and research institutions. One study of scientific influences by Douglas Sprugel in 1980 concluded that of the seventy-seven recognized American scientists dominant in the field of ecology from 1900 to the early 1950s, no fewer than forty-six were students of Cowles or were directly influenced by professional mentors who had been students of Cowles.
The Chicago school of ecology is generally regarded as one of the most influential forces in the development of ecological studies. While Cowles's theories of ecological community and plant succession have been modified and extended by more recent generations of scientists, they continue to be considered among the most significant departures in the modern understanding of the natural environment.
In 1967, the Biological Sciences Division's proposal for a merger of the Departments of Botany and Zoology was approved. The merger, which formed the Department of Biology, responded to the need for flexibility in the use of resources and funding, as well as broader trends in research and teaching in the biological sciences.
Scope Note
The records of the University of Chicago's Department of Botany include administrative files, publications, memorabilia and artifacts, and a large collection of photographs documenting plant life, environmental phenomena, and departmental activities.
Series I: Office of the Chairman, includes records of the activities of the chair of the Department of Botany, spanning the years 1882-1972. The bulk of material in this series represents the chairmanships of John M. Coulter, Henry C. Cowles, Ezra J. Kraus, John M. Beal and Charles E. Olmsted. Predominant in this series are materials collected for annual reports; materials collected for annual appointment and budget reviews; and faculty recruitment materials. Also included in this series is correspondence regarding grants and development; material related to the Faculty Campaign Committee; pamphlets on the history of the department, compiled by Charles E. Olmsted; correspondence and other material documenting the Department of Botany's administrative relationship to the Department of Zoology and the Department of Pharmacology; chairmanship recommendations; and early issues of Botanical Gazette collected by Charles E. Olmsted.
Series II: Friends of Our Native Landscape, contains publications and other material generated by this conservation group. Material in this series includes copies of Friends of Our Native Landscape's bulletins, as well as items relating to organization and membership in the group.
Series III: Bird Haven, contains memorabilia, publications and other material associated with the Robert Ridgway Memorial Bird Sanctuary and Arboretum, known as Bird Haven. Material in this series includes guest register logs, correspondence, ephemera and conservation publications.
Series IV: Memorabilia, includes three items from the Department of Botany, including two decorative pieces and a departmental guest register. Also included in this series are botanical specimens collected by Charles J. Chamberlain and his students.
Series V: Guides to Photographs, contains information about many of the images collected in Series VI. This series contains catalogues, inventories, and informal lists of photographs held in the Department of Botany. These guides are now obsolete in terms of describing the organization and classification of these images; however, the guides do contain additional descriptive content and information about photographers, dates, and the uses of the photograph collections.
Series VI: Photographs, constitutes the largest and best-documented component of the collection. Most of these images have been digitized and described as part
of American Environmental Photographs, 1891-1936, an electronic resource available online. This series contains over 4,000 photographs documenting natural environments, ecologies, and plant communities in the United States at the end of the nineteenth and the beginning of the twentieth century. Many of the photographs were produced by faculty such as Henry Chandler Cowles and George Damon Fuller during departmental field trips, and were later used for research and teaching. The photographs provide an overview of important representative natural landscapes in the United States. Other photographs in this series represent botanists, including faculty and staff in the department. The items in this series are primarily black and white prints, negatives and slides in small or medium-sized formats. There is some duplication of images.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
Browse finding aids by topic.
American Environmental Photographs, 1891-1936 [electronic resource]
Architectural Drawings Collection. Elevations of Wychwood estate
Henry C. Cowles. Collection
Charles E. Olmsted. Papers
Paul D. Voth. Papers
Subject Headings
Beal, John M.; Chamberlain, Charles Joseph, b. 1863; Coulter, John Merle, 1851-1928; Cowles, Henry Chandler, 1869-1939; Fuller, George D. (George Damon), 1869-; Kraus, Ezra J.; Nichols, George E. (George Elwood), 1882-1939; Olmsted, Charles E.;;;; University of Chicago. Department of Botany; Bird Haven; Friends of Our Native Landscape; Botany -- Photographs; Botany -- Research; Canyons -- United States; Cliffs -- United States; Coasts -- United States; Deserts -- United States; Ecological succession; Ecology; Floodplains -- United States; Forests and forestry -- United States; Landforms -- United States; Mountains -- United States; Prairies -- United States; Swamps -- United States; Uplands -- United States; Wychwood, Lake Geneva, Wis.;;;;;; Indiana Dunes National Lakeshore (Ind.); Botanists; Ecologists; Botanical specimens
INVENTORY
- Series I: Office of the Chairman
  The records of the office of the department chairman span the years 1882-1972, with the bulk of material representing the chairmanships of John M. Coulter, Henry C. Cowles, Ezra J. Kraus, John M. Beal and Charles E. Olmsted.
  Three types of files are predominant in this series: Material collected for compiling annual reports, such as correspondence, faculty vitae, reports, financial material, publications, and drafts of annual reports; material collected for annual appointment and budget reviews, including budget and salary recommendations, financial material, and related correspondence; and material related to faculty recruitment, including letters of recommendation and other correspondence, publications and biographical material.
  Also included in this series is correspondence regarding grants and development; material related to the Faculty Campaign Committee; pamphlets on the history of the department, compiled by Charles E. Olmsted; correspondence and other material documenting the Department of Botany's administrative relationship to the Department of Zoology and the Department of Pharmacology; chairmanship recommendations; and early issues of Botanical Gazette collected by Charles E. Olmsted.
  - Annual report materials, 1949-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual report materials, Wychwood, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Annual report materials, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Annual report materials, faculty activities, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Annual report materials, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Annual report materials, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Annual report materials, graduate traineeships, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Budget and appointment materials, 1919-1940 (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
  - Budget and appointment materials, Frederick L. Milthorpe, 1942- 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Budget and appointment materials, 1944-1950 (Box 2, Folder 7-9)
  - Budget and appointment materials, 1949-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1-14)
  - Budget and appointment materials, Lawrence Bogorad, 1955- 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Budget and appointment materials, retired staff, 1948-1965 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Budget and appointment materials, retired staff, 1951-1964 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, 1941-1944 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, Oswald Tippo, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, 1959-1965 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, Richard A. Dilley, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, Frederick L. Milthorpe, 1964-1965 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, 1965-1968 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, Roderick Clayton, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, Harold Evans, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, Albert List, Jr., 1966 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, Roderick MacLeod, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Faculty recruitment materials, Walter Bertsch, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Departmental announcements, 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Administrative correspondence, 1953-1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Campaign Committee materials, 1956-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - Norma E. Pfeiffer, correspondence, 1964-1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Department of Pharmacology, correspondence, 1957-1960 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Departmental history pamphlets, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Merger of departments of Botany and Zoology, correspondence and recommendations, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Department chairmanship nominations, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Fragment of unidentified document, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Botanical Gazette, 1882-1883 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series II: Friends of Our Native Landscape
  This series contains copies of Friends of Our Native Landscape's bulletins, dating from 1945-1961, as well as a small number of items relating to the group's organization and membership, such as announcements, a handbook, and a membership list.
  - Handbook, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Organizational and membership material, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Bulletins, 1945-1949 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins, 1950-1961 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
- Series III: Bird Haven
  This series contains memorabilia and other material from Bird Haven, including three guest register logs, correspondence, ephemera and conservation publications.
  - Guest register and clippings, 1938-1954 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Guest register, correspondence and notes, 1952-1962 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Guest register, 1962-1969 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Handbill, invitation and conservation publications, 1898-1929 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Memorabilia and Artifacts
  Memorabilia in this series includes three items from the Department of Botany, including two decorative pieces and a departmental guest register. Also included in this series are botanical specimens collected by Charles J. Chamberlain and his students. Some of these specimens are mounted on glass slides, while others are encased in wax blocks. Chamberlain and his students often included identifying information on the boxes in which the specimens are housed. An anastigmat, used for the production of lantern slides and associated with Charles J. Chamberlain, is also found in this series.
  - John M. Coulter, reproduction of portrait, 1925 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Wood album cover, unidentified (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Guest register, 1949-1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Charles J. Chamberlain, seven boxes of botanical specimens in wax blocks, circa 1921 (Box 9)
  - Charles J. Chamberlain, six boxes of botanical specimens in wax blocks, circa 1921 (Box 10)
  - Charles J. Chamberlain, five boxes of botanical specimens mounted on glass slides, circa 1921 (Box 11)
  - Charles J. Chamberlain, anastigmat, circa 1921 (Box 12)
- Series V: Guides to Photographs
  This series contains catalogues, inventories, and informal lists of photographs held in the Department of Botany, many of which are now included in Series VI of this collection. These guides are now obsolete in terms of describing the organization and classification of these images; however, the guides do contain additional descriptive content and information about photographers, dates, and the uses of the photograph collections. Not all of the photographs mentioned in these guides are included in Series VI.
  This series is divided into 6 subseries to distinguish among the types of guides included. The first four subseries consist of card files that were likely to have been first compiled by students under Henry C. Cowles. The remaining subseries contain material from a variety of sources in the Department of Botany.
  Subseries 1: Index of Species by State, is a card file organized alphabetically by U.S. state. This file indexes the photographs according to the Latin name of species represented.
  Subseries 2: Index of Individuals, Groups and Locations, is a card file organized alphabetically by name. This file indexes the photographs according to the names of subjects represented, including faculty, staff, student and professional groups, events, and geographic locations.
  Subseries 3: Index of Miscellaneous Subjects, is a card file organized alphabetically. This file indexes the photographs according to subjects and scientific processes represented. Most of the indexed terms are scientific, including common and Latin botanical names.
  Subseries 4: Index of Miscellaneous Subjects by Foreign Location, is a card file organized alphabetically by country, continent, or other region. This file indexes the photographs according to subjects represented, including species and other scientific subjects, as well as individuals, groups, and locations.
  Subseries 5: Catalogues and Lists, includes several short guides to a variety of parts of the photograph collection. These guides were compiled by several different faculty and students around the 1920s-1940s. Most of these guides do not contain detailed information about the images, but were meant to serve as basic inventories of parts of the photograph collection.
  Subseries 6: Boxes, Envelopes and Sleeves, includes many of the original containers in which the images were housed for processing or transport. Many of these containers are annotated, or have stamps or other identifying information.
  - Subseries 1: Index of Species by State
    - Alabama (Box 13)
    - Alaska (Box 13)
    - Arizona (Box 13)
    - Arkansas (Box 13)
    - California (Box 13)
    - Colorado (Box 13)
    - Connecticut (Box 13)
    - Delaware (Box 13)
    - Florida (Box 13)
    - Hawaii (Box 13)
    - Idaho (Box 13)
    - Illinois (Box 14)
    - Indiana (Box 14)
    - Iowa (Box 14)
    - Kansas (Box 14)
    - Kentucky (Box 14)
    - Louisiana (Box 14)
    - Maine (Box 14)
    - Massachusetts (Box 14)
    - Maryland (Box 14)
    - Michigan (Box 14)
    - Michigan (Box 15)
    - Missouri (Box 15)
    - Minnesota (Box 15)
    - Mississippi (Box 15)
    - Montana (Box 15)
    - Nebraska (Box 15)
    - Nevada (Box 15)
    - New Hampshire (Box 15)
    - New Jersey (Box 15)
    - New Mexico (Box 15)
    - New York (Box 15)
    - North Carolina (Box 15)
    - Ohio (Box 15)
    - Oklahoma (Box 15)
    - Oregon (Box 15)
    - Pennsylvania (Box 15)
    - South Dakota (Box 15)
    - Tennessee (Box 15)
    - Texas (Box 15)
    - Utah (Box 15)
    - Washington (Box 15)
    - Wisconsin (Box 15)
    - Wyoming (Box 16)
  - Subseries 2: Index of Individuals, Groups, Events and Locations
    - A-Z (Box 16)
  - Subseries 3: Index of Miscellaneous Subjects
    - A-L (Box 16)
    - L-Z (Box 17)
  - Subseries 4: Index of Miscellaneous Subjects by Foreign Location
    - Canada (Box 17)
    - Abyssinia (Box 18)
    - Africa (Box 18)
    - Algeria (Box 18)
    - Argentina (Box 18)
    - Asia (Box 18)
    - Austria (Box 18)
    - Belgium (Box 18)
    - Brazil (Box 18)
    - Chile (Box 18)
    - China (Box 18)
    - Congo (Box 18)
    - Cuba (Box 18)
    - Denmark (Box 18)
    - Egypt (Box 18)
    - England (Box 18)
    - Europe (Box 18)
    - France (Box 18)
    - Germany (Box 18)
    - Guatemala (Box 18)
    - Holland (Box 18)
    - India (Box 18)
    - Indonesia (Box 18)
    - Ireland (Box 18)
    - Italy (Box 18)
    - Japan (Box 18)
    - Kenya (Box 18)
    - Mexico (Box 18)
    - New Guinea (Box 18)
    - New Zealand (Box 18)
    - Philippines (Box 18)
    - Portugal (Box 18)
    - Russia (Box 18)
    - Samoa (Box 18)
    - Scotland (Box 18)
    - South Africa (Box 18)
    - South America (Box 18)
    - Sri Lanka (Box 18)
    - Sweden (Box 18)
    - Switzerland (Box 18)
    - Tahiti (Box 18)
    - Tanzania (Box 18)
    - Thailand (Box 18)
    - Uruguay (Box 18)
    - Unidentified (Box 18)
    - British Columbia, Canada (Box 18)
    - British Columbia, Canada (Box 19)
    - Manitoba, Canada (Box 19)
    - Nova Scotia, Canada (Box 19)
    - Ontario, Canada (Box 19)
    - Quebec, Canada (Box 19)
    - Saskatchewan, Canada (Box 19)
    - Unsorted cards (Box 19)
  - Subseries 5: Catalogues and Lists
    - Catalogue of negatives, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Lists of photographs by state, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Merle C. Coulter, list of lantern slides, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Classification and lists of lantern slides, circa 1920s-1940s (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Lists of photographs, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 6: Boxes, Envelopes and Sleeves
    - Mailing envelopes (Box 21)
    - Glass plate boxes (Box 21)
    - Negative sleeves (Box 22)
- Series VI: Photographs, circa 1891-1936
  This series contains thousands photographs documenting natural environments, ecologies, and plant communities in the United States at the end of the nineteenth and the beginning of the twentieth century. Many of the photographs were produced by faculty such as Henry Chandler Cowles and George Damon Fuller during departmental field trips, and were later used for research and teaching. The photographs provide an overview of important representative natural landscapes in the United States. Other photographs in this series represent botanists, including faculty and staff in the department. In addition to locations in the United States, there are images of foreign locations, as well as photographic reproductions of diagrams, graphs and charts.
  The items in this series are primarily black and white prints, negatives and slides in small or medium-sized formats. There is some duplication of images.
  This series is divided into eight subseries. Subseries 1-7 are organized by format, with each subseries then organized by state. Coded numbers assigned during digitization processing can be used to uniquely identify individual images; however, these numbers do not represent the original organization or classification of the photographs. Subseries 8: Unsorted Photographs, consists of images in a variety of formats; these images have not been organized or described in detail.
  Additional descriptive information about some of these photographs is found in Series V. Most of these images have also been digitized, with detailed descriptions, as part of American Environmental Photographs, 1891-1936, an electronic resource available online.
  - Subseries 1: Prints